

Louis Lippens

POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCHER

Ghent University (FEB), Sint-Pietersplein 6, 9000 Gent, Belgium

☑ Louis.Lippens@UGent.be | ☆ louislippens.be | ☑ Louis-Lippens | ☑ lglip | ☐ louislippens

About Me

I am a **postdoctoral researcher** in **labour economics** at Ghent University. My academic work focuses on what determines and solves labour market discrimination. My **postdoctoral project** delves into the relationship between **competition** and **discrimination**. More broadly, as an affiliated researcher at **UGent @ Work**, I collaborate on **interdisciplinary projects** addressing key challenges in the **labour market**, translating research results into **evidence-based policy advice**. I hold a **master's degree** in **work psychology** from Ghent University and a business degree in **general management** from Vlerick Business School. Prior to re-entering academia and obtaining a **joint PhD in economics and sociology** from Ghent University and Free University Brussels, I worked in management consulting, where I gained experience in data governance and data analytics.

Employment

ACADEMIA (FULL-TIME)

Ghent University Ghent, BE

Postdoctoral Researcher

• FWO postdoctoral fellowship project on how market competition can diminish labour market discrimination, using advanced statistical techniques such as multilevel meta-regression on transnational data

· Co-lecturer Labour Economics course

UGent @ Work Ghent, BE

AFFILIATED RESEARCHER

Jun. 2021 – Present

- Research on topics in labour economics, contributing to solving economic and societal questions surrounding the (Belgian) labour market
- Translation of labour market research into evidence-based policy advice

Ghent University Ghent, BE

DOCTORAL RESEARCHER Aug. 2019 – Sep. 2023

- Teaching assignments, such as guiding last-year students with their master's thesis, coaching bachelor students on migration research topics, and giving guest lectures on empirical/experimental economic research
- Development of low-threshold, interactive, and flexible tools (e.g. multicultural situational judgment tests) to increase the awareness of HR professionals' intercultural competence and to empower them to deal with the drivers of their competence
- · Dissertation on (ethnic) hiring discrimination, its determinants, its mechanisms, and the influence of the organisational context

Free University Brussels Brussels Brussels, BE

VISITING DOCTORAL RESEARCHER

Aug. 2019 - Jul. 2023

Oct. 2023 - Present

• Research on topics in sociology of labour

PRIVATE SECTOR (FULL-TIME)

BDO Flanders region, BE

SENIOR CONSULTANT (DATA ANALYTICS)

Oct. 2018 - Jul. 2019

- Performed survey research on the modal shift in transportation and developed a predictive model for a governmental body and an inland port
- · Advised a private company active in the entertainment industry on the design of a data asset repository
- Constructed a financial model for a mid-scale mobility management project

Capgemini Invent Brussels, BE

CONSULTANT (DATA GOVERNANCE)

Sep. 2017 - Sep. 2018

• Performed a benchmark study of data governance operating models in financial services

- · Developed and optimised various data asset documentation processes in the context of BCBS239 and GDPR regulatory frameworks
- · Conducted a data quality maturity assessment across various business and functional departments within a major Belgian bank
- Set up data-sharing agreements between various business and functional departments within a major Belgian bank

SOCIAL SECTOR (PART-TIME)

Ghent, BE

Human Capital Director

Jul. 2015 – Jun. 2016

- 180DC is the world's largest international consultancy for non-profits and social enterprises
- Led the human capital activities of 180DC's Ghent University branch
- · Conducted selection tests, incl. reasoning tests and structured interviews, of about 70 university students
- · Other activities: implementation of 180° feedback system, social media marketing, event support

180 Degrees Consulting

Ghent, BE

Mar. 2015 - Jun. 2015

• Co-developed an integrated fundraising and marketing strategy for the NGO Join For Water

- Conducted survey research regarding the brand perceptions of Join For Water's donors and sympathizers
- · Developed an evidence-based, bespoke brand personality for Join For Water, as well as brand improvement guidelines

Education

MANAGEMENT CONSULTANT

Ghent University Ghent, BE

 PhD, ECONOMICS
 Aug. 2019 – Aug. 2023

- Doctoral courses: Advanced Econometrics (Non-Linear Techniques), Advanced Labour Economics, Multilevel Analysis
- Other courses: Econometrics, Labour Economics, Advanced Academic Writing in English, Multilevel Analysis in R, Generalised Linear Models in R, Multidisciplinary Research Tools to Study Work and the Labour Market, Effective Graphical Displays
- · Supervisors: Prof. Stijn Baert, Prof. Eva Derous

Free University Brussels

Brussels, BE

PhD, Sociology Aug. 2019 – Aug. 2023

• Supervisor: Prof. Pieter-Paul Verhaeghe (Joint PhD with UGent as the main institution)

Vlerick Business School

MM, GENERAL MANAGEMENT (MAGNA CUM LAUDE)

Sep. 2016 - Jun. 2017

Ghent BF

- Key Courses: Corporate Finance, Financial Accounting, Management Accounting and Control, Strategic Management, Operations Management
- Electives: Big Data and Data Analytics, Digital Strategy (w/ BNPP Fortis), Strategy and Organisational Design, Mergers and Acquisitions (w/ Gimv)
- Bootcamp: Strategic Innovation in Renewable Energy (w/ Durabilis)

Ghent University Ghent, BE

MSc, Industrial and Organisational Psychology (Magna Cum Laude)

Sep. 2011 - Jun. 2016

- · Key Courses: Multi-level Organisational Research, Statistics, Applied Data Analysis, Human Resource Management, Industrial Relations
- Master's thesis: Short form of the Wilde Intelligenztest: Psychometric qualities and utility of a 12-minute intelligence test for personnel selection

Publications

PEER-REVIEWED PUBLICATIONS

2023 European Economic Review

The state of hiring discrimination: A meta-analysis of (almost) all recent correspondence experiments

L Lippens, S Vermeiren, S Baert

2023 International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health

Beyond the Hype: (How) Are Work Regimes Associated with Job Burnout?

K du Bois, P Sterkens, L Lippens, S Baert, E Derous

2023 Labour Economics

Understanding ethnic hiring discrimination: A contextual analysis of experimental evidence

L Lippens, A Dalle, F D'hondt, PP Verhaeghe, S Baert

2022 Applied Economics Letters

Ethnic discrimination on paper: Uncovering realtors' willingness to discriminate with mystery mails

A Ghekiere, L Lippens, S Baert, PP Verhaeghe

2022 **Journal of Ethnic and Migration Studies**

Is labour market discrimination against ethnic minorities better explained by taste or statistics? A systematic review of the empirical evidence

L Lippens, S Baert, A Ghekiere, PP Verhaeghe, E Derous

2021 **Economics Letters**

Loss aversion in taste-based employee discrimination: Evidence from a choice experiment

L Lippens, S Baert, E Derous

2021 PLOS ONE

How do employees think the COVID-19 crisis will affect their careers?

L Lippens, E Moens, P Sterkens, J Weytjens, S Baert

DISCUSSION PAPERS

2023	arXiv
------	-------

Computer says 'no': Exploring systemic hiring bias in ChatGPT using an audit approach

L Lippens

2022 IZA Institute of Labour Economics

An Arab, an Asian, and a Black guy walk into a job interview: ethnic stigma in hiring after controlling for social class

H Van Borm, L Lippens, S Baert

2022 IZA Institute of Labour Economics

Selecting names for experiments on ethnic discrimination

S Baert, L Lippens, H Van Borm

 $Visit\ my\ Google\ Scholar\ profile\ at\ https://bit.ly/louis-lippens-scholar\ for\ a\ comprehensive\ overview\ of\ my\ research.$

Services and Outreach __

PEER REVIEW

In addition to conducting my own research, I have also reviewed the work of some of my peers. I have served as a reviewer (ad hoc) for American Sociological Review (1), Journal of Labor Economics (1), Technology in Society (1), Journal of Ethnic and Migration Studies (1), Social Science & Medicine (1), Social Forces (1), PLOS ONE (2), Journal of Sociology (1), Work and Occupations (1), Social Policy and Society (1), International Migration Review (1), The Annals of Regional Science (1), Oxford Bulletin of Economics and Statistics (1), International Journal of Manpower (1), and Economics Bulletin (2).

ACADEMIC OUTREACH

2023	Artificial Intelligence and The Economy	Berlin, DE
	Computer says 'no': Exploring systemic hiring bias in ChatGPT using an audit approach	Deriiri, DL
2022	Belgian Day for Labour Economists	Brussels, BE
	Understanding ethnic hiring discrimination: A contextual analysis of experimental evidence	Diusseis, DL
2022	CESSMIR Conference	Ghent, BE
	Understanding ethnic hiring discrimination: A contextual analysis of empirical evidence	Griefit, DL
2022	IMISCOE Annual Conference	Oslo, NO
	The state of hiring discrimination: A meta-analysis of (almost) all recent correspondence experiments	0510, 110
2022	Spring Meeting of Young Economists	Orléans, FR
	The state of hiring discrimination: A meta-analysis of (almost) all recent correspondence experiments	Oneuns, i k
2021	CESSMIR Conference	Ghent, BE
	The state of hiring discrimination: A meta-analysis of (almost) all recent correspondence experiments	Griefit, DL
2021	EALE Annual Conference	Barcelona, ES
	Is labour market discrimination against ethnic minorities better explained by taste or statistics?	(online)
2021	Day of Sociology	Utrecht, NL
	Taste-based discrimination: Actually a matter of contact avoidance?	(online)
2021	CESSMIR Research Day	Ghent, BE
	Taste-based discrimination: Actually a matter of contact avoidance?	Griefit, DL
2021	Faculty of Economics and Business Administration Research Day	Ghent, BE
	Loss aversion in taste-based employee discrimination: Evidence from a choice experiment	OHEH, DL
2020	Context Matters Symposium	Brussels, BE
	Is labour market discrimination against ethnic minorities better explained by taste or statistics?	บเนรระเร, DL

SOCIETAL OUTREACH

2023	VRT NWS Onderzoek discriminatie arbeidsmarkt	News broadcast
2023	De Standaard Oud is out, vooral op de Europese werkvloer	Newspaper article
2023	Radio 1 Nog altijd discriminatie rond leeftijd en afkomst op arbeidsmarkt	Radio interview
2023	Het Nieuwsblad; Gazet van Antwerpen Oud is out, vooral in Europa	Newspaper article
2023	Het Belang van Limburg Bedrijven discrimineren meer op leeftijd en looks dan op etniciteit	Newspaper article
2023	De Morgen Wie jong en knap is, heeft de grootste kansen op de arbeidsmarkt	Newspaper article
2023	Het Laatste Nieuws Hoe knapper je bent, hoe meer kans op een job	Newspaper article
2023	Le Soir L'âge, le physique et le handicap, premier facteurs de discrimination à l'embauche	Newspaper article
2022	Measuring intentions to discriminate: in writing, open and exposed	Blog post
2022	UGent @ Work Ethnic labour market discrimination: Generalisation or aversion?	Blog post
2022	HR Magazine The structured interview best predicts a good match	Magazine article
2022	LinkedIn The top-ranked selection tools to hire the best-performing candidate	Blog post
2021	Het Laatste Nieuws Oudere sollicitanten krijgen bijna 50 procent minder positieve reacties	Newspaper article
2021	Trends (magazine) Leeftijdsdiscriminatie op arbeidsmarkt is erger dan etnische discriminatie	Newspaper article
2021	UGent @ Work Does discrimination have a price?	Blog post
2021	Radio 1, Nieuwe Feiten Loonopslag of liever werken met alleen autochtone Vlamingen?	Radio interview
2020	Apache Trainingen tegen arbeidsmarktdiscriminatie	Newspaper article
2020	Het Laatste Nieuws Mijn job verdwijnt, mijn loon wordt kleiner, mijn promotie wordt gefnuikt: Dit is hoe de Vlamingen denken over de toekomst van hun werk	Newspaper article

Skills_____

GENERAL SKILLS

Research	Analytics	Business
Audit studies – Survey research – Experimental research – Applied psychometrics	(Ordered) logit models – Linear models – Meta-analysis – Meta-regression – Reliability and validity analysis – Structural equation modeling	Project management – Human capital management – Corporate finance – Advisory

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Coding Languages	Research Software	Business Software	Creative Software	Other
R (ggplot2, tidyverse, hugo, xaringan, quarto) – SQL	RStudio – Stata – SPSS – Knime	Collibra – MS Office	Photoshop – GIMP – Ableton Live	Git – Markdown – LaTeX

Skill	Dutch	English	French
Reading	C2	C2	C1
Writing	C2	C2	B1
Listening	C2	C2	B2
Speaking	C2	C1	B1

Note. CEFR: A1/A2: Basic User; B1/B2: Independent User; C1/C2: Proficient User.

high client focus and professional approach to private partnerships.

Honors, Grants, and Awards

2023	FWO Junior Postdoctoral Fellowship	FWO Research
	Following (international) peer review of my postdoctoral project on competition and discrimination, I was	Foundation –
	awarded a three-year postdoctoral fellowship starting October 2023 (award rate: 21.2%).	Flanders
2017	Student Achievement for Outstanding Performance	Vlerick Business
	Personal recognition for obtaining the most and highest positive peer evaluations in group assignments	School
	throughout the academic year.	301001
2015	Best European Consulting Branch	
	180 Degrees Consulting Ghent was named the best overall European branch (Europe) of the world's largest	180 Degrees
	consultancy for non-profits and social enterprises. We were lauded for our collaboration-fostering spirit,	Consulting